[Music]
regular apple intake is associated with
all sorts of good things like
living longer particularly a lower risk
of dying from cancer
here's the survival curve of elderly
women who don't eat an apple a day
10 years out nearly a quarter died and
15 years out nearly half were gone
but those who averaged like a half an
apple a day didn't drop off as fast and
those eating an apple a day more than
three and a half ounces like a cup of
apple slices stayed around even longer
yeah but maybe people who eat apples
every day just happen to practice other
healthy behaviors like exercising more
or not smoking and that's really why
they're living longer
well they controlled for most of that
obesity smoking status poverty diseases
exercise so as to compare
apples to apples so to speak but what
they didn't control for was an otherwise
healthier diet
studies show that those who regularly
eat apples have higher intakes and not
just nutrients like fiber found in the
apples but they're eating less added
sugar less saturated fat in other words
they're eating overall healthier diets
and so no wonder apple eaters live
longer but is apple eating just a marker
for healthy eating or is there something
about the apples themselves that's
beneficial
you don't know
until you put it to the test
there's all sorts of fun studies like
this where subjects were randomly
assigned the morning to nothing a
caffeinated energy drink black coffee or
an apple given that athletes use a
variety of common strategies to
stimulate arousal cognition and
performance before their morning
training
did the apple hold its weight
yes appearing to work just as well as
the caffeinated beverages
the problem with these kinds of studies
though is they're not blinded those in
the apple group knew they were eating an
apple and so there may have been this
expectation bias placebo effect that
made them unconsciously give that extra
bit of effort in the testing and skew
the results
you just can't stuff a whole apple into
a pill
that's why researchers instead test
specific extracted apple components so
they can perform a double-blind
placebo-controlled study where half get
the fruit elements half get the sugar
pill and you don't know until the end
who got which
the problem there though is that you're
no longer dealing with a whole food
removing the symphony of interactions
between the thousands of phytonutrients
in the whole
apple most of these special nutrients
are concentrated in the peel though
instead of just dumping millions of
pounds of nutrition in the trash why
couldn't researchers just dry and powder
the peels into opaque capsules to
disguise them and then run blinded
studies with that
even just a small amount could greatly
increase phytochemical content and
antioxidant activity
the meat industry got the memo dried
apple peel powder decreases microbial
expansion in meat and protects against
carcinogen production when you cook it
and one of the carcinogens formed during
the grilling of meat is a beta-carboline
alkaloid a neurotoxin which may be
contributing to the development of
neurological diseases like parkinson's
i did a video about it a while ago
uncooked meat doesn't have any
the neurotoxin is formed when you cook
it
but you can cut the levels in half by
first marinating the meat with dried
apple peel powder and also cuts down the
amount of fecal contamination bacteria
in the meat fecal bacteria growing
before
and after the addition of dried apple
peel powder in pork beef and turkey
apple peels can also inhibit the
formation of genotoxic dna damaging
heterocyclic amines cutting the effects
of these cooked meat carcinogens by up
to more than half
in view of the risks associated with
consuming these cancer-causing compounds
in meat there is a need to reduce
exposure by
blocking hea formation such as adding
apple powder during the cooking of meats
to help prevent their production i mean
i can't think of any other way to reduce
exposure what about consuming apple
peels directly dried apple peel powder
was found to exhibit powerful
anti-inflammatory and antioxidant action
but this was in
mice does it have anti-inflammatory
properties in people you don't know
until you put it to the test a dozen
folks with moderate loss of joint range
of motion and associated chronic pain
were given a spoonful of dried apple
peels a day for 12 weeks
and pain scores dropped month after a
month and the range of motion improved
in their neck shoulders back and hips
conclusion consumption of dried apple
peel powder was associated with improved
joint function and pain reduction
why just associated because there was no
control group so they might have all
been just getting better on their own or
it could have been a placebo effect but
hey why not give apple peels a try by
eating more
apples
[Music]
foreign